OpenAI just released a new version of
GPD5 specially trained for coding. This
is exclusively available within their
codeex environment. You can access it in
terminal in an IDE and on web and this
is much better at code reviews than the
previous versions. So it's really
specialized specifically for coding. It
seems to be much better at coding tasks
even compared to GPT5 on high settings
and for complex tasks it can run
independently for more than 7 hours. So
long horizon coding tasks are in reach
now. So this is a specialized optimized
version of GPT5 which they're calling
GPT5 codeex. They really need to work on
their naming. It's getting really
confusing. But this is a specialized
model trained for real world software
engineering workflows. And you're going
to see later in the video that they have
focused on real world software
engineering tasks including code reviews
and it's a much better at long horizon
tasks.
So CEX is now available everywhere. So
there is a cloud version within chat
GPT. There is even a code review version
and you can use it either through the
CLI or IDE extension. I think it's
available in VS code and cursor at the
moment and it's part of your chart GPT
subscription. So it's going to be
available to plus pro business education
and enterprise plans. You don't have to
pay anything extra. Keep in mind there
are some rate limits but I think they
are pretty generous. So first a quick
look at some benchmarks. The first one
that they have reported is the sweep
bench verified. It seems to be a couple
of percent better than the existing GPD
5 on high settings. It also has the same
reasoning efforts, low, medium, high.
[snorts] Now, something you will notice
is that this is not the actual reported
score of GPT5 Hive. Actually, if you go
back to the initial announcement of
GBD5, it was 74.9%
on the Sweepbench verified. But you'll
notice that it was using only 477
questions out of the 500s that are
available on Sweepbench verified. In
fact, any previous model that was
trained and tested on Sweepbench
verified from OpenAI were tested on 477
questions. But now for this test they
are testing it on all 500 questions and
you can actually see that the GBT 5 high
has a huge performance decrease. So it
seems like for the remaining 22
questions GPT5
is struggling a lot and same seems to be
the case with GPT5 codeex on high
settings as well because it's not able
to even beat this score. So that being
said, 23 questions are still a
significant portion and I'm actually
glad that they started adding those. Now
when it comes to code refactoring tasks,
it's easily I would say 50% better than
GPD5 on high settings, which is pretty
incredible. But I personally think this
is the most important chart of this
release. And it really shows where these
coding agents are going. In order to
explain that chart, let's look at this.
So according to them, for the bottom 10%
of the user turns in terms of the number
of tokens generated, GPD5 uses
93% or almost 94% fewer tokens than
GPD5. GPD5 codeex. But for the top 10%,
GPD5 codeex thinks more spending twice
as long and editing, testing, and
iterating. So if you look here, this has
the ability to dynamically select the
reasoning effort and then also how many
tokens it's going to generate. So for
low reasoning or low effort tasks, it's
generating a lot a lot less tokens
compared to GPD5. But where the
complexity of the task increases, it's
generating almost twice the number of
tokens of GPD5. Now hopefully these are
useful tokens based on the results that
we saw from the benchmarks but you can
actually see that the model has the
ability now to think longer for complex
tasks and this is one of the promise of
GBT5 type of models that they are going
to have this dynamic routing but here
even it's dynamically selecting the
effort that is going to put in based on
the complexity of the task. So here they
say GP5 codeex adopts how much time it
spends thinking more dynamically based
on the complexity of the task. As I said
this is going to be pretty incredible if
it works and the model combines two
essential skills for coding agents. So
pairing with developers in interactive
sessions. So you can actually use it as
a chat model and then you can offload
the work which the model can do
independently for longer tasks. And the
beauty of Codex as a product is that you
can run it locally on CLI and then if
you want you can just offload some tasks
to the cloud version which runs in the
cloud independent of your input which is
a pretty great user experience. Another
aspect that they have specifically
focused on is code reviews. Now software
engineers do a lot of code reviews. So
they say that GPT5 codex has been
trained specifically for conducting code
reviews and finding critical flaws. When
reviewing it navigates your codebase
reasons through dependencies and runs
your code and tests it in order to
validate correctness. I personally have
been mostly using clot code but I am
going to definitely try GBD5 codecs and
see how good this model is. So based on
their internal benchmarks, the number of
incorrect comments has reduced
substantially. It went from 13% all the
way down to almost 4% which is pretty
incredible. The number of high impact
comments generated by GPT5 codeex
compared to GPT5 has increased again by
a good 12 to 13%. And that being said
that it has actually reduced the average
number of comments per PR which is
pretty good as well. Now these updates
are available in CEX CLI. You can also
use this as a part of IDE. For example,
VS code and cursel have support for
codec cla but I don't know how the
experience is going to be because I
think these are different integrations.
Although the underlying model is the
same, but depending on the interface
that you're using, I think you may run
into different experience. From what I
have seen and heard, Codex CLI seems to
be the purest experience where you can
get the best results. So, I'm going to
do some tests with Codeex CLI and Codeex
in the IDE and we'll probably report
this in another video. people who had
early access to this model seems to
really like it and open aim. I'm also
open to early access. Okay. So here is
Dan. I think he is part of the every or
CEO or co-founder of every. So he says
there are two important things. Dynamic
thinking time. They moved this pattern
from Chad GPT to their coding model.
It's going to be standard going forward.
Right? So the model itself can decide
how much thinking effort it needs to
spend based on the complexity of the
task and then local to web handoff. So
your agent should be with you with full
context wherever you use it. Now the
beauty is that you can start a task in a
CLI and then hand it off to the web
version of codeex and according to these
reports it seems to be working. So by
default, Codex runs in a sandbox
environment with network access
disabled. This is for the safety because
it's going to be running code and you
don't want the agent to run either
malicious code or perform some
destructive actions. It's a similar
pattern that we have seen in other CLIs
including clot code, Gemini CLI and I
think that is the right way to go now
with these updates. Codex CLI definitely
is catching up to clot code which is
great for us customers and consumers.
Now pricing and availability. So this is
part of chartp plus pro business
education in enterprise. I think they
have pretty generous rate limits for
each of these, but they say that with
plus edu and business seats can cover a
few focused coding sessions each week
while pro can support a full work week
across multiple projects. Right? So do
check it out and see if you run into any
issues. Now this does not seem to be
available through API yet. They say for
developers using Codex CLI via the API,
we plan to make GPD5 CEX available in
the API soon. So, I think it's going to
be available pretty soon. Okay, I'm
going to be testing GPD5 codecs in
Codeex CLI. It's really hard to keep
track of how many codecs there are.
Watch out for the that video. Anyways, I
hope you find this video useful. Thanks
for watching and as always, see you in
the next